Edwin Francis Carpenter papers, 1917-1963
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Edwin Francis Carpenter papers, 1917-1963
MS 332
Carpenter, Edwin Francis, 1898-1963
Papers, 1917-1963 (bulk 1930-1960), of astronomer Edwin F. Carpenter, 1898-1963. Includes biographical materials, correspondence, publications and appearances, printed materials, photographs, and glass slides. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence documenting his professional activities, and photographs documenting the building and instrumentation of Steward Observatory at the University of Arizona, and Kitt Peak National Observatory in the Quinan Mountains, west of Tucson, Arizona. Selected correspondents include Bart Bok, Raymund Dugan, Stuve Holm, Knut Lundmark, Otto Struve, Harlow Shapley, and Edwin Hubble.
2.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Born on 1 November 1898 in Boston, Massachusetts, Edwin Carpenter received the A.B. and A.M. degrees from Harvard and the Ph. D. from the University of California at Berkeley (1925). He began his teaching duties at the University of Arizona that year, and became head of the Astronomy Department (1936), director of Steward Observatory (1938), a member at large of the board of directors of the Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy, Inc. (AURA).
His career brought considerable attention to The University of Arizona, and raised the research and instructional levels of its astronomy and observation programs. Mr. Carpenter’s research included investigations of characteristics of galaxies, the death of stars through supernovae, and white dwarf stars. He was active in campus affairs, and served as local president for several organizations, including the American Association of University Professors and Society of Sigma Xi. Nationally, he was vice-president and chairman of the Astronomical Divisions of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and council member of the American Astronomical Society. He published widely, and received support for his work from the National Science Foundation, National Academy of Sciences, and the American Philosophical Society of Philadelphia. He died on 11 February 1963 at Tucson. He had nearly completed the two-year undertaking of relocating Steward Observatory’s 36 inch reflector to the new site at Kitt Peak National Observatory. He was survived by his wife, Ethel, and children Roger and Emily.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Biographical Materials, 1920-1929
Series II: Correspondence, 1917-1963
Series III: Publications and Addresses, 1925-1959
Series IV: Printed Materials, 1932-1963
Series V: Photographs, 1932-1963
Series VI: Glass Slides, 1938-1957
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1917-1963 (bulk 1930-1960), of astronomer Edwin F. Carpenter, 1898-1963. Includes biographical materials, correspondence, publications and appearances, printed materials, and photographs. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence documenting his professional activities, and photographs documenting the building and instrumentation of Steward Observatory at the University of Arizona, and Kitt Peak National Observatory in the Quinan Mountains, west of Tucson, Arizona. Selected correspondents include Bart Bok, Raymund Dugan, Stuve Holm, Knut Lundmark, Otto Struve, Harlow Shapley, and Edwin Hubble.
Access Terms
Bok, Bart Jan, 1906 -- Correspondence
Dugan, Raymond Smith, 1878-1940 -- Correspondence
Holm, Sture, 1936 -- Correspondence
Lundmark, Knut Emil, 1889-1958 -- Correspondence
Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972 -- Correspondence
Struve, Otto, 1897-1963 -- Correspondence
Steward Observatory
Kitt Peak National Observatory
Astronomers -- Arizona -- Biography
Astronomical observatories -- Arizona
Correspondence
Photographs
Related Material
Materials in collection number AZ 330 relate to the Conference on the Use of Solar Energy, Tucson, 1955.
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 1920-1929
  - Biographical materials. 1920-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical materials: notes compiled by Ethel Carpenter. 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Biographical materials: student coursework given and taken by EFC. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1917-1963
  - Correspondence, general (mostly incoming, some outgoing replies). 1917-1938 (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
  - Correspondence, general, 1939-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, Southwestern Division, 1936-39 about 19th meeting in Alpine Texas, and dedication of the McDonald Observatory. 1936-1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Astronomical Society, 1936-1949. Chiefly concerning the planning for the 82nd meeting held in Tucson Dec. 28-31, 1949. 1936-1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Edwin Hubble. 1929-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1937-1938, about funds for purchase of a recording microdensitometer, type B, from P.J. Kipp & Zonen, Delft, Holland. 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bailey Telescope. 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Colorimeter. 1950-1959 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Conference: on Applied Solar Energy, Tucson and Phoenix 1955.(EFC edited the proceedings, access number TJ810/A82). 1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conference: On Astronomical Research in Small Academic Departments, 1954- 1958. Held at Swarthmore College, with follow up conference 1957. 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Shapley, Harlow. 1923-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - University of Arizona, 1938-1946. Chiefly with the Dean, College of Liberal Arts. 1938-1946 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series III: Addresses, 1925-1959
  - Publications by EFC. 1925-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Popular lectures, presentations, addresses, seminars. 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speeches. 1939, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Printed Materials, 1932-1963
  - Printed materials: programs and listing from International Astronomical Union, 1932-58. Includes materials from 10th meeting, Moscow, 1958. 1932-1958 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Printed materials: general astronomical meeting programs. 1929-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Printed materials: poems and humorous materials regarding astronomy; also includes "Monthly Astronomical News Letter," issued by B. Bok, 1942?-1944? numbers 4, 6, 7, 17, 18, 19. 1942?-1944? (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed materials: clippings on Steward Observatory and Kitt Peak National Observatory. 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
- Series V: Photographs, 1932-1963
  - "Calver" telescope, 12 inch, brought to Tucson from Cameron, Ariz.. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Bailey" telescope, designed by EFC, lens procured by Dana F. Bailey. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory, 1957-62. Includes site views, construction, buildings, instruments. 1957-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory, building at 950 N. Cherry, Tucson. 1959-1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Steward Observatory reflector, and its move to Kitt Peak. 1959-1963 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Kitt Peak: Dedication of Robert R. McNath Solar Telescope. 1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Steward Observatory, site searches. 1930s-1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Steward Observatory, addition to campus building. 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Tucson Amateur Astronomers, and their "Moon watch" event. 1957 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, 1949-1955. Chiefly of A.A.A.S. Tucson, 1949; and Solar Energy Conferences in Tucson and Phoenix. 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1932-1948. Includes unidentified astronomical formations; "Eclipse Camp," in Maine, 1932; Mount Palomar dedication. 1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Observatories and equipment: includes postcards of observatories from a 1932 trip to Europe, and various sites in the United States, including Perkins (Delaware, Ohio) and Griffith (Los Angeles, Calif.). 1932 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Glass Slides, 1938-1957
  - Arizona Movie Set, 1939; Gila River, 1941; Salt River Canyon, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - University of Arizona vs. New Mexico Military Institute Polo Game, 1940 February 10; University of Arizona Inauguration Day 1938, April 12; University of Arizona Campus Scenes; 1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)